# **Alex Walter**



M.Sc. (Health,) Pg.Cert.(Pres.,) B.Sc.(Hons.,) E.C.P./P.P., M.C.Para

Consultant Paramedic

(General Practice)

#### **PROFILE**

Consultant level Advanced Clinical Practitioner and independent prescriber from a paramedical background with extensive emergency, urgent and primary care experience in both rural and urban settings.

Very experienced working within Urgent Care and Treatment Centres, Walk in Centres, Minor Injuries Units, Accident & Emergency Departments, Out of Hours GP services, GP surgeries and within the community setting.

Confident senior healthcare manager with a strategic overview whilst maintaining tactical effectiveness and used to delivering results on time and in budget.

Experienced tutor, mentor, lecturer, supervisor, assessor. Due to deliver a keynote address at College of Paramedic's 2024 Annual Conference on Frailty care and link between Ambulance and Primary Care Paramedics.

# REGISTRATION AND MEMBERSHIP

Health and Care Professions Council 'Paramedic' – Reg. No. – PA10961 with Independent and Supplementary Prescribing Annotation.

College of Paramedics - Full Member and sits on national committee for Primary and Urgent Care.

#### **CONTACT**

73 Congreve Road Worthing, BN14 8EN, UK +44 (0)7710 169310 alex@bpms.org.uk

### REFERENCES

Clinical, professional, employment and personal character references are available on request.

## PROFESSIONAL CLINICAL EXPERIENCE

Consultant Paramedic

• The Petworth Surgery (2023 to present)

Working effectively as one of the GPs within scope of practice – seeing patients autonomously for acute and chronic issues. Managing chronic disease, hypertension lead for the practice, supporting the care homes on weekly virtual ward rounds. Non-medical education lead, working with multiple universities. Clinically supervising medical / paramedic / nursing students, trainee Physician Assistants, trainee Advanced Clinical Practitioners and GP Registrars. Acting as Duty Clinician for Practice on a rotation basis and supporting the nursing / HCA team as needed. Supporting Practice Manager to modernise the practice and support the non-clinical as well as clinical teams through a number of changes in processes and procedures.

#### Consultant Paramedic

• Brighton and Hove GP Federation (2023 to present)

Working remotely providing telephone consultations for the extended access service across all Brighton and Hove GP Practices.

Consultant Paramedic (2021 to 2023,) Advanced Paramedic Practitioner (2017-2021,) Specialist Paramedic Practitioner (2008-2017)

- The Coppice Surgery / Angmering Medical Centre 2017-2023
- Integrated Care 24 Ltd 2014-2023
- Queen Victoria Hospital, East Grinstead 2011-2014
- North East London NHS FT, Barking 2010-2012
- Self employed Locum 2009-2018

Leading the 'On-The-Day' team at the surgery with all acute enquiries, managing patient flow through the surgery, both real and virtual. Clinical Frailty Lead for the Primary Care Network and Lead for non-medical education within the surgery. Managing and delivering the 'ward rounds' for the surgery's care and nursing homes.

Working as an autonomous Consultant Paramedic undertaking a full range of primary care services in a GP surgery, seeing 'on the day' urgent patients, completing home visits and undertaking Learning Disability, Dementia & Frailty Annual Reviews, administering immunisations, telephone & video triage / consultations, phlebotomy and completing Anticipatory Care Plans, ReSPECT and DNACPR forms. Referring patients to secondary care and community specialists, following up on referrals, ordering investigations and undertaking Multi-Disciplinary Reviews of frail patients.

Working in various NHS Walk-in-Centres, Urgent Care / Treatment Centres, Accident & Emergency departments and Minor Injuries Units, dealing with injuries, illnesses, plastering, suturing, ordering and interpreting x-rays, acting as shift manager and line managing junior nurse practitioners, nurses and healthcare assistants.

Undertaking medical assessments on behalf of insurance companies of prospective lives to be assured, including taking observations, near patient testing of urine, phlebotomy and detailed medical health history taking and undertaking phlebotomy directly for pathology labs for employment purposes and private patients.

Working in out of hours GP settings, doing base appointments, home visiting and telephone consultations. Providing Clinical Supervision to GP Registrars (ST1, ST2 and ST3) on behalf of Kent, Surrey and Sussex Deanery and healthcare practitioners on pathway to First Contact Practitioner and Advanced Clinical Practitioner qualifications.

Page 1 Alex Walter

#### **LEADERSHIP SKILLS**

Experienced senior manager within an NHS Foundation Trust, planning and delivering trust wide aims and goals without losing focus on the day to day running of the resuscitation department.

Confident duty manager running a busy walk in centre whilst maintaining clinical skills.

Efficient clinical team leader and duty manager of a city within an NHS Foundation Ambulance Trust.

#### **TEACHING / MENTORING**

Very experienced teacher / lecturer with assessing skills. Capable clinical supervisor of both medical and healthcare professionals.

#### **LOCUM LOCATIONS**

Urgent Care Centres, A&Es:-Croydon University Hospital Medway Maritime Hospital Princess Royal University Hospital The Royal London Hospital

GP Surgeries:-

Willow Green, East Preston Henfield Medical Centre

Walk in Centres / Minor Injury Units:-

Barking, London
Dagenham, London
New Addington, Croydon
Soho, London
Victoria, London
Whitechapel, London

#### **VOLUNTARY ROLES**

School Governor, LEA Infant School, 2014-2019 Welfare Officer, Affiliated club to British Gymnastics, 2014 to present.

Chairperson and Expedition Leader, Duke of Edinburgh's Award, Brighton & Hove 1993 - 2004

#### PROFESSIONAL CLINICAL EXPERIENCE (continued)

Resuscitation Officer / Professional Lead for Resuscitation

Sussex Community NHS FT 2014-2017

Responsible for the training of resuscitation skills across the whole spectrum of staff, clinical and non-clinical staff. Responsible for the auditing of staff training and resuscitation equipment. Line managing the Resuscitation Trainers. Responsible for the Resuscitation Department budget. Responsible for the development and maintenance of the Resuscitation Policy and parts of other policies, such as Deteriorating Patient Policy, End of Life Care Policy and DNACPR related matters as well as devising, writing and delivering training in other areas of care, such as ECG acquisition and basic interpretation and recognising the deteriorating patient. Supporting the delivery of the Health Care Assistants' Care Certificate programme. Reporting to the Chief Nurse and Medical Director.

#### Paramedic Practitioner

• South East Coast Ambulance NHS FT, Brighton 2006-2010

Working alone in the community to deliver an emergency response to 999 calls with the aim of reducing unnecessary Emergency Department admissions through the use of holistic patient assessments, community-based referrals and direct acute admission (where unavoidable) to the appropriate specialty. Receive referrals from other Community-based health professionals and NHS 111 for assessments to be undertaken with treatments as appropriate.

Clinical Team Leader

South East Coast Ambulance NHS FT, Brighton 2004-2006

Undertaking a full range of Paramedic duties and managing a team of Paramedics / Ambulance Technicians on a day to day basis. Also undertaking the role of Duty Manager on a shift rotation basis for the ambulance service within the City of Brighton and Hove.

Paramedic / Ambulance Technician

• South East Coast Ambulance NHS FT, Brighton 2000-2004

Working alone on a rapid response car and on a double crewed ambulance to deliver emergency healthcare within the community in response to 999 calls, undertaking high dependency inter-facility transfers and mentoring junior colleagues.

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Research Analyst

American Express Services Europe Ltd 1998-2000

Working in Business Engineering to support the further role out and development of a new telephone customer service platform, delivering non-paper based direct debit sign up scheme and setting up Route Cause Analysis and Continuous Process Improvement Teams.

Senior Customer Service Representative / Line Instructor

American Express Services Europe Ltd 1994-1998

Providing world class customer service to Amex Cardmembers across all products and delivering training to new starters and existing staff on new products. Facilitating the smooth adoption of a new telephone customer service platform.

Service Manager

• Heathfield Motoring Centre 1993-1994

Managing a busy service garage in a motoring centre and supporting staff in the sales department, rental department and parts, spares & accessories shop.

Various Student Jobs

Multiple employment agencies

Various temporary part time jobs during university vacations, including, labourer in a water pump company, bar person in hotels, pubs and nightclub and a waiter.

#### **TRAINING**

Menopause, 2023, Red Whale

IR(ME)R for non-medical referrers, 2022, eLfH.

Dermoscopy for beginners 2022, Primary Care Dermatology Society, London

FCP/ACP Roadmap for Clinical Supervisors, 2021, Health Education England, remote.

Essentials of Dermatology I & II, 2020, Primary Care Dermatology Society, London.

Paediatric Presentations in Primary Care, 2018, M&K Update, London

Abdominal Assessment Masterclass, 2017, M&K Update, London

*Telephone Consultation Course*, 2017, Royal College of General Practitioners, London.

The A&E Radiology Survival Course for Doctors, 2013, Northwick Park Hospital, London

Ear, Nose and Throat Top Ten Conditions, 2012, Practitioner Development UK, Guy's Hospital, London.

Radiation Protection for Referrers, 2011, King's College Hospital NHS Foundation Trust, BHR Hospitals, Barking.

Minor Surgical Procedures, 2011, Practitioner Development UK, St. Thomas's Hospital, London.

Paediatric Emergency Care, 2008, American Academy of Pediatrics, run at Conquest Hospital, Hastings

Asthma Care for Practice Nurse, 2006, Brighton and Hove Teaching Primary Care Trust.

Wound Care, 2005, East Surrey Hospital, Redhill.

Acute Thrombolysis in AMI, 2004, Boehringer Ingelheim Ltd / Sussex Ambulance Service, Brighton

#### **EDUCATION**

M. Sc. Health

2011-2021 (delayed completion due to family bereavements & CoVID-19) Health & Social Care Faculties, Universities of Brighton and London South Bank

- The Advanced Assessment of the Presenting Adult
- The Advanced Assessment of the Presenting Child
- Developing Skills and Competence in Professional Practice Through Work Based Learning
- Research in Health and Social Care
- Leading and Transforming Services
- Research Methods and Critical Appraisal
- Mentorship
- Dissertation Paramedics in General Practice: an extended literature review.

P.G. Cert. (Independent Prescribing)

2019-2021 (delayed completion due to CoVID-19)

Medway School of Pharmacy, University of Greenwich and University of Kent

- Non-medical prescribing in context
- Safe and effective prescribing
- Consultation and decision making
- Putting prescribing into practice

Emergency Care Practitioner / Paramedic Practitioner (ECP / PP)

2006-2008 (equivalent to graduate diploma – 120 credits at Level6.)

Faculty of Health and Social Care Sciences, St. George's, University of London and University of Kingston

- Nature of Physical Assessment
- Clinical Decision Making
- Management of Minor Illness
- Management of Minor Injury
- Applied Pharmacology
- Paediatrics
- Working with Older People
- Mental Health.

#### **Paramedic**

2003, Institute of Health and Care Development, EDEXCEL

Ambulance Technician

2000-2001, Institute of Health and Care Development, EDEXCEL

Trainer and Assessor

1998-1999, City and Guilds NVQ C23 & D32

B. Sc. (Hons.), Chemistry with Management Studies

1990-1993, University of Sussex

#### **CONFERENCES PRESENTED AT**

Frailty: How Primary Care and Ambulance Paramedics can help each other, 2024, College of Paramedics National conference, Leeds

Primary Care Paramedics and Prescribing, 2023, Conference Chairperson, College of Paramedics Primary Care conference, Leeds

Advanced Paramedic Practitioners – the future for Urgent Care? 2014, Advancing Paramedic Practice for Urgent Care Conference, Birmingham, SBK Healthcare Events

Utilising the Role of Emergency Care Practitioners to Manage Urgent Demand Efficiently, 2014, Whole System Approaches to Urgent Care Redesign Conference, Manchester, SBK Healthcare Events.

Redesigning Clinical Pathways to Redirect Patients Away from the Emergency Department, 2014, Whole System Approaches to Urgent Care Redesign Conference, Manchester, SBK Healthcare Events.

Communication in Unscheduled Care – getting it right! 2013, Annual Royal College of Nursing's Emergency Care Association Conference, Brighton, RCN Events.

Emergency Care Practitioners and A&E, 2008, Annual Royal College of Nursing's Emergency Care Association Conference, Warrington, RCN Events

# CONFERENCES ATTENDED

(in addition to those above)

College of Paramedics National Conferences UK, 2014 – 2023 (inclusive.)

European Resuscitation Council 2015 Guidelines Launch Congress, Prague, Czech Republic, 2015

European Resuscitation Council 2015 Guidelines Education Congress, Reykjavik, Iceland, 2016

# **LECTURING / TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

Diploma in Primary and Urgent Care - Examiner College of Paramedics, 2023

Working as an examiner in OSCEs for the above diploma, accredited by St Georges, University of London and supporting the writing and development of the Diploma.

Resuscitation & First Aid Training Self-employed 1995-present

Delivering the annual required training for all health and social care workers, teaching to the standards set by the UK Resuscitation Council. Teaching First Aid to members of the public for general first aid, first aid at work, paediatric first aid, use of Automated External Defibrillator and anaphylaxis training (including auto-injector use.) Delivering a combination course of School's First Aid to local maintained and private schools.

DNACPR / ReSPECT / NEWS2 Training Self-employed 2015-present

Delivering training to healthcare workers on Do Not Attempt Cardio-Pulmonary Resuscitations orders, the Recommended Summary Plan for Emergency Care and Treatment and the National Early Warning Score, version 1, then version 2.

Clinical Mandatory Training

The Health and Safety Group Limited, London 2014-2018

Delivering the annual required training for health and care professionals covering:-Health and Safety at Work, Control of Substances Hazardous to Health, Caldicott Principles, Equality & Diversity, Fire Safety Awareness, Infection Control, Food Hygiene, Manual Handling - (Including Practical Sessions,) Basic Life Support - (Including CPR Practical Sessions,) Safeguarding Vulnerable Adults, Safeguarding Children, Conflict Management and Lone Working.

Transfer of the critically III / Injured Patient (TRIIP)
Brighton and Sussex University Hospitals NHS Trust (BSUH) 2007-2011

Member of faculty for BSUH, on their TRIIP course, lecturing A&E and ITU nurses and doctors, as well as anaesthetists, operating department practitioners and recovery nurses.

Chemical, Biological, Radiological, Nuclear and explosives (CBRNe)
South East Coast Ambulance Service NHS Foundation Trust 2006-2010

Teaching all aspects of the course for category 1 responders (Ambulance Services and Acute NHS Trusts) with regard to the decontamination of patients and category 1 responders.

Ambulance Aid

British Red Cross, Kent and Sussex 2001-2010

Teaching and assessing all aspects of Ambulance Aid, together with underpinning theoretical knowledge for ambulance crews. Developing and delivering continuous professional development courses for experienced ambulance crews. Lead Assessor for Institute of Health and Care Development, EDEXCEL, for Kent and Sussex.

June 2024 Alex Walter